<document celex="IP-08-103" lang="en">
 <p align="right">
  <b>
   IP/08/103
  </b>
 </p>
 <p align="right">
  Brussels, 29 January 2008
 </p>
 <h1>
  <a name="Heading4">
  </a>
  <b>
   Sustainable Energy Cities take the lead on
climate change: the European Commission launches the Covenant of
Mayors
  </b>
 </h1>
 <h2>
  <a name="Heading7">
  </a>
  <b>
   <i>
    Today the European Commission launched the Covenant
of Mayors, the most ambitious initiative to date involving the citizens in the
fight against global warming. It comes after an informal consultation with
numerous cities across Europe, whose Mayors will join the Commission in
launching the Covenant. The Covenant consists of the formal commitment of the
adhering cities to go beyond the objectives of the EU in terms of reducing their
CO
   </i>
  </b>
  <sub>
   <b>
    <i>
     2
    </i>
   </b>
  </sub>
  <b>
   <i>
    emissions through energy efficiency
and renewable energy actions. Almost 100 cities throughout Europe, including 15
capital cities, have expressed their early support for the Covenant.
   </i>
  </b>
 </h2>
 <p>
  "Cities are becoming the places to deliver new ideas and innovative projects
against global warming. Cities are also the public spaces where it is
possible to find multicultural, cross-sectoral solutions, where the
necessary conciliation between private and public interests may
be found. The approach to tackle the climate crisis challenge can only
be holistic, integrated, long-term and, most of all, based on the
participation of citizens. This complex picture is best managed at local level.
Cities must therefore become leading actors for implementing sustainable energy
policies, and must be supported in their effort", said European Commissioner for
Energy Andris Piebalgs.
 </p>
 <p>
  The Covenant of Mayors will be a result-oriented initiative, focusing on
concrete projects and measurable results. The adhering cities and regions will
formally commit to reduce their CO
  <sub>
   2
  </sub>
  emission by more than 20% by
2020, by developing Sustainable Energy Action Plans. Citizens will be informed
of the achievements of their respective cities through periodic reports, which
can be monitored by a third party.
 </p>
 <p>
  The Commission will give support to the sharing of the best sustainable
energy practices in the world to the Covenant cities and regions through a
'benchmarks for excellence' mechanism. The Commission also intends to negotiate
the terms of the involvement of other major stakeholders in the Covenant. A
Covenant secretariat, funded through the Intelligent Energy Europe programme,
will facilitate monitoring, networking and promotion tasks of this new
challenge.
 </p>
 <p>
  The proposed Covenant text comes as a result of an informal consultation with
a broad number of cities throughout Europe. As a result, almost one hundred
cities throughout Europe, including 15 capital cities, have expressed their
early interest in the Covenant. Elected representatives from London, Helsinki,
Riga, Berlin, Bonn, Milan, Venezia, Nantes, Ljubljana, Warsaw and other cities
will attend the launching event, together with Commissioner Piebalgs and
President of the Committee of the Regions Michel Delebarre.
 </p>
 <p>
  Now it is time to produce a final version of the Covenant, through a formal
consultation, and to open the period to formalise adhesions to the Covenant. In
parallel, a number of high level debates and events will take place to work out
the terms of participation of financial entities and the benchmarks for
excellence in the Covenant. The first group of Covenant cities will formalise
their adhesion no later than the next EU Sustainable Energy Week.
 </p>
</document>
