<document celex="IP-08-1019" lang="en">
 <p align="right">
  <b>
   IP/08/1019
  </b>
 </p>
 <p align="right">
  Brussels, 26 June 2008
 </p>
 <h1>
  <a name="Heading4">
  </a>
  <b>
   Statement by Vice-President Barrot on the
occasion of the International Day against Drug Abuse and Illicit Trafficking
– 26 June 2008
  </b>
 </h1>
 <h2>
  <a name="Heading7">
  </a>
  <b>
   <i>
    On the occasion of the International Day against
Drug Abuse and Illicit Trafficking, an evaluation of international anti-drug
efforts has been launched. This examination is being conducted under the terms
of the political agreement reached during the 1998 UN General Assembly Special
Session (UNGASS) on the global drug problem. Ten years later, the results of
this evaluation will be used to redefine international objectives in the fight
against drugs and the political commitments made by the participating countries.
As a global actor, the European Union will take part in this evaluation.
Vice-President Jacques Barrot, responsible for justice, freedom and security
matters, has made a statement on this occasion.
   </i>
  </b>
 </h2>
 <p>
  The Commission is aware of the importance of the role that it will have to
play in the development of a common EU position. If Europe is to be increasingly
present on the international scene and make its voice heard, there must be
closer coordination between the Union and the Member States. EU actions at
international level to fight drug abuse and illicit trafficking will be informed
by the awareness that responsibility for the worldwide drug problem is shared by
all countries.
 </p>
 <p>
  "Fighting the drug problem effectively requires strategies that are based on
facts and that can be adapted to respond to new situations; this is not about
ideology or political dogma, but rather choosing actions that work in practice"
said Vice-President Barrot.
 </p>
 <p>
  For years, the Commission's position has been based on an approach balancing
prevention and treatment, on the one hand, and repression of drug trafficking,
on the other. In 2004 Europe devised a strategy to combat drugs for the period
2005-2012. This strategy is set out in detail in two consecutive four-year
action plans. The plans provide a precise framework of actions, a clear
allocation of responsibilities and a timetable for implementing the objectives.
Evaluation tools based on clear and measurable indicators have been designed so
that the situation can be correctly evaluated.
 </p>
 <p>
  With this in mind, the Commission will be paying close attention to the final
evaluation exercise of the first four-year action plan (2004-2008) and the
launch of the new action plan (2009-2012), both of which represent the practical
expression of its 2005-2012 anti-drug strategy. The evaluation will be presented
in a communication in the autumn of 2008.
 </p>
 <p>
  The third Eurobarometer Report on young people's attitudes towards the
various types of drugs, published today by the Commission, comes at an opportune
moment. The Vice-President is pleased that young people have shown an interest
in European policy in this area.
 </p>
 <p>
  <b>
   To find out more about Vice-President Barrot's work, please see his
website:
  </b>
 </p>
 <p>
  <a href="http://www.ec.europa.eu/commission_barroso/barrot/welcome/default_en.htm">
   http://www.ec.europa.eu/commission_barroso/barrot/welcome/default_en.htm
  </a>
 </p>
 <p>
  <b>
   The Eurobarometer Report is available at:
  </b>
 </p>
 <p>
  <a href="http://ec.europa.eu/public_opinion/index_en.htm">
   http://ec.europa.eu/public_opinion/index_en.htm
  </a>
 </p>
</document>
