<document celex="IP-08-1002" lang="en">
 <p align="right">
  <b>
   IP/08/1002
  </b>
 </p>
 <p align="right">
  Brussels, 25
  <sup>
   th
  </sup>
  June 2008
 </p>
 <h1>
  <a name="Heading4">
  </a>
  <b>
   The Commission launches Single European Sky
II for safer, greener and more punctual flying
  </b>
 </h1>
 <h2>
  <a name="Heading7">
  </a>
  <b>
   <i>
    The European Commission adopted today the second
package of legislation for a Single European Sky (SES II). These proposals aim
to further improve safety, cut costs and reduce delays. That will in turn mean
lower fuel consumption, so that airlines could save up to 16 million tons of
CO
   </i>
  </b>
  <sub>
   <b>
    <i>
     2
    </i>
   </b>
  </sub>
  <b>
   <i>
    emissions and cut their annual cost
by between two and three billion euros. This full reform of the European air
traffic management system will be key to managing the doubling of traffic
expected by 2020. Not only airline passengers, but also freight forwarders and
military and private aviation will benefit. The package will create additional
jobs in aviation. Meanwhile, European manufacturing industry will gain from
being at the forefront of innovation in air traffic management technology (i.e.
satellite based systems - Galileo, datalink, etc.), thus giving it a competitive
edge on global markets.
   </i>
  </b>
 </h2>
 <p>
  Commission Vice-President responsible for transport, Antonio Tajani, said:
"This package is a win-win for passengers, for Europe's economy and for the
environment. The skies in Europe are still fragmented. As a consequence, flights
are on average 49 km longer than needed. Our proposal aims at helping reduce
queues to take off and land, passengers will have more chance of arriving on
time. At the same time the package will help us deliver safer and greener
flying, while creating more capacity."
 </p>
 <p>
  The SES II package is based on four pillars: updates to existing legislation
from 2004; the SESAR ATM (Single European Sky Air Traffic Management Research)
Master Plan or 'technological pillar'; the 'safety pillar' and an airport
capacity action plan.
 </p>
 <p>
  The first pillar introduces
  <b>
   several enhancements to the original SES
legislation (see
  </b>
  <a href="http://europa.eu/rapid/pressReleasesAction.do?reference=IP/01/1398&amp;format=HTML&amp;aged=0&amp;language=EN&amp;guiLanguage=en">
   IP/01/1398
  </a>
  <b>
   )
  </b>
  ,
including binding performance targets for air navigation service providers, a
European network management function to ensure convergence between national
networks and a definitive  date for Member States to improve performance
,initially through a cross border cooperative approach known as Functional
Airspace Blocks.
 </p>
 <p>
  The new package places
  <b>
   environmental issues
  </b>
  at the core of the Single
European Sky and improved air traffic management should realise its potential to
reduce greenhouse gas emissions from aviation. Prospective improvements are up
to 10% per flight, which amounts to 16 million tons of CO
  <sub>
   2
  </sub>
  savings
per year and a reduction of annual costs by â&sbquo;Ź2.4 billion.
 </p>
 <p>
  The
  <b>
   technological pillar
  </b>
  focuses on introducing better technology. The
SESAR programme brings together all aviation stakeholders to develop and operate
a new generation, Europe-wide air traffic management system. Its deployment will
enable the safe, sustainable and cost-effective handling of twice the current
traffic by 2020.
 </p>
 <p>
  The
  <b>
   safety pillar
  </b>
  provides for increased responsibilities for the
European Aviation Safety Agency. This would ensure precise, uniform and binding
rules for airport safety, air traffic management and air navigation services, as
well as sound oversight of their implementation by Member States.
 </p>
 <p>
  Finally, the
  <b>
   airport capacity pillar
  </b>
  tackles the shortage of runways
and airport facilities, which currently threatens to become a major bottleneck.
The initiative seeks to co-ordinate better airport slots issued to aircraft
operators with air traffic management measures as well as the establishment of
an airport capacity observatory to fully integrate airports in the aviation
network.
 </p>
 <p>
  For further information see
  <a href="http://europa.eu/rapid/pressReleasesAction.do?reference=MEMO/08/432&amp;format=HTML&amp;aged=0&amp;language=EN&amp;guiLanguage=e">
   MEMO/08/432
  </a>
  and
  <a href="http://ec.europa.eu/transport/air_portal/traffic_management/index_en.htm">
   http://ec.europa.eu/transport/air_portal/traffic_management/index_en.htm
  </a>
 </p>
</document>
