<document celex="IP-08-1025" lang="en">
 <p align="right">
  <b>
   IP/08/1025
  </b>
 </p>
 <p align="right">
  Brussels, 26 June 2008
 </p>
 <h1>
  <a name="Heading4">
  </a>
  <b>
   Environment: Commission takes nine member
states to Court over environmental liability
  </b>
 </h1>
 <h2>
  <a name="Heading7">
  </a>
  <b>
   <i>
    The European Commission has decided to refer nine
Member States to the European Court of Justice for failing to transpose the EU
directive on liability for damage to the environment into their domestic law.
The deadline was 30 April 2007. The nine are Austria, Belgium (concerning the
Brussels region only), Greece, Finland, France, Ireland, Luxembourg, Slovenia
and the United Kingdom.
   </i>
  </b>
 </h2>
 <p>
  Environment Commissioner Stavros Dimas said: "The Environmental Liability
Directive implements the polluter-pays principle and is one of the most
significant new pieces of EU environmental law of the last few years. More than
a year after the deadline it is high time these nine Member States transposed
it, not least to create the necessary legal security for operators carrying out
activities falling under the directive and to avoid distortions in its
implementation. This could arise, for instance, in the case of damage affecting
more than one Member State."
 </p>
 <p>
  The Environmental Liability Directive (ELD) establishes a legal framework for
environmental liability based on the polluter-pays principle, with the aim of
preventing and remedying environmental damage. Natural and legal persons who
operate or control activities listed in the directive are strictly liable for
the damage they cause to the environment through their activity. The
environmental damage covered is damage to protected species or natural habitats,
water bodies or soil.
 </p>
 <p>
  The Commission on 1 June 2007 sent a first written warning to 23 Member
States that had not transposed the directive at that time. Fourteen of those
have since done so.
 </p>
 <p>
  <b>
   Legal Process
  </b>
 </p>
 <p>
  Article 226 of the Treaty gives the Commission powers to take legal action
against a Member State that is not respecting its obligations.
 </p>
 <p>
  If the Commission considers that there may be an infringement of EU law that
warrants the opening of an infringement procedure, it addresses a "Letter of
Formal Notice" (first written warning) to the Member State concerned, requesting
it to submit its observations by a specified date, usually two months.
 </p>
 <p>
  In the light of the reply or absence of a reply from the Member State
concerned, the Commission may decide to address a "Reasoned Opinion" (second and
final written warning) to the Member State. This clearly and definitively sets
out the reasons why it considers there to have been an infringement of EU law
and calls upon the Member State to comply within a specified period, normally
two months.
 </p>
 <p>
  If the Member State fails to comply with the Reasoned Opinion, the Commission
may decide to bring the case before the European Court of Justice. Where the
Court of Justice finds that the Treaty has been infringed, the offending Member
State is required to take the measures necessary to conform.
 </p>
 <p>
  Article 228 of the Treaty gives the Commission power to act against a Member
State that does not comply with a previous judgement of the European Court of
Justice, again by issuing a first written warning (“Letter of Formal
Notice”) and then a second and final written warning (“Reasoned
Opinion”). The article then allows the Commission to ask the Court to
impose a financial penalty on the Member State concerned.
 </p>
 <p>
  <b>
   Further information:
  </b>
 </p>
 <p>
  For rulings by the European Court of Justice see:
 </p>
 <p>
  <a href="http://curia.eu.int/en/content/juris/index.htm">
   http://curia.eu.int/en/content/juris/index.htm
  </a>
 </p>
 <p>
  For more information on the Environmental Liability Directive:
 </p>
 <p>
  <a href="http://ec.europa.eu/environment/liability/index.htm">
   http://ec.europa.eu/environment/liability/index.htm
  </a>
 </p>
</document>
