<document celex="IP-08-1016" lang="en">
 <p align="right">
  <b>
   IP/08/1016
  </b>
 </p>
 <p align="right">
  Brussels, 26 June 2008
 </p>
 <h1>
  <a name="Heading4">
  </a>
  <b>
   Lower charges, greater consistency, more
competition: Commission consults on bringing down mobile phone tariffs in
Europe
  </b>
 </h1>
 <h2>
  <a name="Heading7">
  </a>
  <b>
   <i>
    Aiming to spur competition among operators and
lower phone charges for European consumers, the Commission today starts a public
consultation on the future regulation of "voice call termination rates" in
the EU based on a draft Commission Recommendation on termination rates. Voice
call termination rates are the wholesale tariffs charged by the operator of
a customer receiving a phone call to the operator of the caller's network.
Included in everyone's phone bill, and therefore eventually paid by the
consumer, these tariffs are determined by the intervention of national telecoms
regulators. At the moment the decisions of the national telecoms regulators
result in very divergent rates across the EU. Mobile termination rates range
from €0.02/min (in Cyprus) to over €0.18/min (in Bulgaria) and are 9
times higher than fixed line termination rates
   </i>
  </b>
  <b>
   <i>
    (on average
€0.0057/min for local call termination). This distorts competition between
operators from different countries and between fixed line and mobile phone
operators. The public consultation on this proposal will be open until 3
September 2008.
   </i>
  </b>
 </h2>
 <p>
  <i>
   "Disparate termination rates across the EU and large gaps between fixed
and mobile termination rates are serious barriers to achieving a Single European
Telecoms market that benefits competition and consumers. The consumer pays the
price for these gaps between national regulatory policies,"
  </i>
  said Viviane
Reding, EU Telecoms Commissioner
  <i>
   . "Call termination markets in the EU need a
regulatory plumber. Over the next 3 years, I expect greater consistency and
coordination to bring the costs for calls into mobile networks down by around 70
per cent from the current level."
  </i>
 </p>
 <p>
  <i>
   "Truly cost oriented termination rates will increase competition to the
benefit of consumers. Consumers should expect to pay lower retail prices as a
result. This Recommendation will also benefit large parts of the telecoms
industry as it is likely to eliminate distortions of competition between fixed
and mobile operators,"
  </i>
  said EU Competition Commissioner Neelie Kroes
  <i>
   :
“It will also reduce the large sums for call termination which smaller
mobile operators have to pay to large operators when they try to compete with
the latter with the very popular flat rate offers. In view of these benefits a
timely implementation of this Recommendation is essential."
  </i>
 </p>
 <p>
  The Commission, after assessing over 770 regulatory proposals by national
regulators over the past 5 years, warned today that price regulation of
termination markets across Europe lacks consistency. It said that gaps between
fixed and mobile termination rates and between mobile termination rates imposed
by national regulators cannot be altogether justified by differences in the
underlying costs, networks or national characteristics. This could have the
following negative effects:
 </p>
 <ul>
  <li>
   Legal uncertainty and increased regulatory burden for operators providing
cross-border services.
  </li>
  <li>
   National regulators bringing down mobile termination rates in their country
risk punishing their own mobile industry if a neighbouring regulator still
allows higher rates.
  </li>
  <li>
   Investment in new networks and services hampered if operators face different
regulation in every country.
  </li>
 </ul>
 <p>
  At present, fixed operators and their
customers are indirectly subsidising mobile operators by paying higher
termination rates for calls made from fixed lines to mobiles. This
cross-subsidisation
  <i>
  </i>
  is estimated at €10 billion in Germany for
1998-2006 (
  <a href="http://ec.europa.eu/information_society/policy/ecomm/doc/library/ext_studies/future_ip_intercon/ip_intercon_study_final.pdf">
   WIK
Consult
  </a>
  ) and €19 billion in the UK, Germany and France for 1998-2002
(
  <a href="http://www.cerna.ensmp.fr/Documents/OB-GLB-F2M-FinalReport.pdf">
   CERNA-Warwick-WIK
  </a>
  ).
 </p>
 <p>
  The Commission today presented a draft Recommendation for convergence of
termination rates in Europe, including clear principles on which cost elements
should be taken into account when national telecoms regulators determine
termination rates, an efficient costing methodology, and symmetric regulation
(where the same price caps apply, within a country, to mobile and fixed
operators, respectively). This will help foster an effective regulatory
environment and avoid distortions such as cross-subsidies from fixed to mobile
consumers. The advice of the European Regulators Group (ERG), which has made
several attempts towards more consistent regulation of termination rates since
2006, was taken into account by the Commission in the draft Recommendation.
 </p>
 <p>
  <b>
   Background
  </b>
 </p>
 <p>
  The Commission will issue the final text of the Recommendation on the
regulatory treatment of fixed and mobile termination rates in October under
article 19 of the Framework Directive of the EU Telecom rules, which allows the
Commission to further harmonise the application of EU Telecoms rules in the
single market to promote competition and consumer benefits. Member States have
to ensure that national regulators take "the utmost account" of Commission
Recommendations.
 </p>
 <p>
  The European Commission's assessment of termination rates is available
at:
 </p>
 <p>
  <a href="http://ec.europa.eu/information_society/policy/ecomm/implementation_enforcement/index_en.htm">
   http://ec.europa.eu/information_society/policy/ecomm/implementation_enforcement/index_en.htm
  </a>
 </p>
 <p>
  The Commission's public consultation document can be found on:
 </p>
 <p>
  <a href="http://ec.europa.eu/information_society/policy/ecomm/library/public_consult/termination_rates/index_en.htm">
   http://ec.europa.eu/information_society/policy/ecomm/library/public_consult/termination_rates/index_en.htm
  </a>
 </p>
 <p>
  The work of the ERG on termination rates is available at:
 </p>
 <p>
  <a href="http://www.erg.eu.int/doc/publications/erg_07_83_mtr_ftr_cp_12_03_08.pdf">
   http://www.erg.eu.int/doc/publications/erg_07_83_mtr_ftr_cp_12_03_08.pdf
  </a>
 </p>
 <p>
  Input to the Commission's public consultation can be sent to:
 </p>
 <p>
  <a href="mailto:infso-termination@ec.europa.eu">
   infso-termination@ec.europa.eu
  </a>
 </p>
 <p>
  <a href="http://europa.eu/rapid/pressReleasesAction.do?reference=MEMO/08/438&amp;format=HTML&amp;aged=0&amp;language=EN&amp;guiLanguage=en">
   MEMO/08/438
  </a>
 </p>
 <p align="center">
  Annex
  <br />
  [ Figures and graphics available in PDF and WORD
PROCESSED ]
  <br />
  Source: European Regulators Group, ERG (08) 17 MTR Update
Snapshot
  <br />
  <br />
  [ Figures and graphics available in PDF and WORD PROCESSED
]
  <br />
  Source: European Electronic Communications Regulation and Markets,
13
  <sup>
   th
  </sup>
  Report
  <br />
  <br />
  [ Figures and graphics available in PDF and WORD
PROCESSED ]
  <br />
  Source: European Electronic Communications Regulation and
Markets, 13
  <sup>
   th
  </sup>
  Report
 </p>
 <p>
  <br />
  [ Figures and graphics available in PDF and WORD PROCESSED ]
 </p>
 <p>
  <b>
   Call termination at local level:
  </b>
  refers to the conveyance of calls
from the local exchange or switch located nearest to the called subscriber to
the premises of the called subscriber where the call is completed.
 </p>
 <p>
  <b>
   Call termination at single transit level:
  </b>
  refers to the conveyance of
calls from a transit switch located at a higher network level through the local
exchange/switch for completion at the called subscriber's premises.
 </p>
 <p>
  <b>
   Call termination at double transit level:
  </b>
  refers to the conveyance of
calls from a transit switch located at a higher network level through two
exchanges/switches for completion at the called subscriber's premises.
 </p>
</document>
