<document celex="IP-08-1003" lang="en">
 <p align="right">
  <b>
   IP/08/1003
  </b>
 </p>
 <p align="right">
  Brussels, 25
  <sup>
   th
  </sup>
  June 2008
 </p>
 <h1>
  <a name="Heading4">
  </a>
  <b>
   "Think Small First": A Small Business Act
for Europe
  </b>
 </h1>
 <h2>
  <a name="Heading7">
  </a>
  <b>
   <i>
    Most jobs in the EU are provided for by Small and
Medium Sized Enterprises (SMEs), companies of 250 employees or less. They have a
crucial importance for the future development, but very often face enormous
bureaucratic hurdles and obstacles. European SMEs deserve to be better assisted
to fully unlock their potential of long term sustainable growth and of more job
creation. To achieve this goal, the European Commission has unveiled today the
Small Business Act for Europe (SBA), based on ten guiding principles and
proposes policy actions to be undertaken by both the Commission and Member
States.
   </i>
  </b>
 </h2>
 <p>
  Commission President José Manuel Durão Barroso said: "
  <i>
   Today's
Small Business Act is a step towards a Europe of entrepreneurs, with less red
tape and more red carpet for Europe's 23 million SMEs. It aims to help small
businesses to thrive and to give the best ones a launch pad to grow into world
beaters. The Small Business Act is a crucial milestone in the implementation of
the Lisbon Strategy for Growth and Jobs. It will mean more responsive public
administrations, less late payment of invoices, access to more help with
finance, innovation and training, lower VAT for services supplied locally and
better access to public procurement contracts. The package will also give SMEs
access to a European Private Company Statute to cut bureaucracy and increase
clarity
  </i>
  "
 </p>
 <p>
  Commission Vice-President Günter Verheugen, responsible for enterprise
and industry policy said
  <i>
   “Entrepreneurs and entrepreneurship are of
enormous importance for our societies. Today and even more so tomorrow small and
medium sized enterprises will provide for professional education and employment
opportunities. Caring about SMEs means therefore caring about present and future
jobs in the EU. Therefore it is high time that an SME friendly policy becomes
mainstream policy in the EU. The Small Business Act is driven by the "Think
Small First principle" and brings the full weight of EU and its Member States
behind small companies. Together we can deliver."
  </i>
 </p>
 <p>
  Internal Market and Services Commissioner Charlie McCreevy said: "
  <i>
   Small
companies across Europe can look forward to a new instrument to do business in
the Single Market. The SPE is transparent, flexible and will offer a strong
label everywhere. I therefore encourage the Council and the European Parliament
to quickly reach an agreement on the Commission's proposal.
  </i>
  "
 </p>
 <p>
  European Investment Bank (EIB) President Philippe Maystadt, added: "
  <i>
   The
analysis of the Commission confirms the conclusions of the EIB's own
consultation exercise: small and medium-sized enterprises wellbeing and growth
will be key to Europe's future competitiveness. The market alone is unable to
provide sufficient and appropriately priced finance for SMEs, in particular for
high growth, innovative businesses. The EIB Group will therefore seek to address
gaps in the market by broadening the scope of its financing.
  </i>
  " 
 </p>
 <p>
  The Commission is proposing a genuine political partnership between the EU
and the Member States reflecting the
  <b>
   political willingness to recognise the
central role of SMEs in the EU economy
  </b>
  and to put in place for the first
time a comprehensive policy framework for the EU and its Member States. The SBA
proposal goes hand in hand with the recently announced plans of the European
Investment Bank Group to simplify, modernise and diversify the range of its
instruments to support SMEs.
 </p>
 <p>
  At the heart of the SBA is the conviction that achieving the best possible
framework conditions for SMEs depends first and foremost on
  <b>
   society’s
recognition of entrepreneurs,
  </b>
  including crafts, micro-enterprises, family
owned or social economy enterprises,
  <b>
   and making the option of starting
one’s own business
  </b>
  attractive. This means that the rather negative
perception of the role of entrepreneurs and risk-taking in the EU must
change.
 </p>
 <p>
  The European Small Business Act sets out 10 principles which should be
adopted at the highest political level and concrete measures that will make life
easier for small businesses. After consulting with businesses and their
representatives, the European Commission has also resolved to
  <b>
   propose new
legislation in four areas
  </b>
  that particularly affect SMEs:
 </p>
 <ul>
  <li>
   First, a new
   <b>
    General Block Exemption Regulation on state aids
   </b>
   will
simplify procedures and reduce costs. It will increase the aid intensity for
SMEs and make it easier for SMEs to benefit from aid for training, research and
development, environmental protection and other types of aid.
  </li>
  <li>
   Secondly, a
   <b>
    new statute for a European Private Company
   </b>
   will allow a
"Société privée européenne" (SPE) to be created and operate
according to the same uniform principles in all Member States. It has been
designed to address the current onerous obligations on SMEs operating across
borders, who need to set up subsidiaries in different company forms in every
Member State in which they want to do business. In practical terms, the SPE
would mean that SMEs can set up their company in the same form, no matter if
they do business in their own Member State or in another. Opting for the SPE
will save entrepreneurs time and money on legal advice, management and
administration
  </li>
  <li>
   Thirdly, a new proposal on VAT will offer Member States the option to apply
   <b>
    reduced VAT rates for locally supplied services, including labour intensive
services,
   </b>
   which are mainly provided by small and medium enterprises.
  </li>
  <li>
   Lastly, an amendment to the directive on
   <b>
    late payments
   </b>
   is foreseen in
2009 to help to ensure that SMEs are paid within the 30 day time limit
stipulated.
  </li>
 </ul>
 <p>
  <b>
   10 principles shall
  </b>
  guide the conception and
implementation of policies at EU and Member State level, such as granting a
second chance for business failures, facilitating access to finance and enabling
SMEs to turn environmental challenges into opportunities.
 </p>
 <p>
  In addition to the standing commitment to
  <b>
   cut administrative burden by 25%
by 2012
  </b>
  , the time needed to
  <b>
   start a new company
  </b>
  should be no more
than one week, the maximum time to obtain
  <b>
   business licenses
  </b>
  and permits
should not surpass one month and
  <b>
   one-stop-shops
  </b>
  should assist to
facilitate start-ups and recruitment procedures.
 </p>
 <p>
  Where practical, the Commission plans to use concrete dates in a year for the
entry into force of
  <b>
   regulations/decisions
  </b>
  affecting business. Member
States are invited to consider similar measures.
 </p>
 <p>
  The SBA includes an ambitious set of measures to allow SMEs to fully benefit
from the Single Market and expand into international markets by orienting more
resources to small companies' access to finance, Research &amp; Development and
innovation. They will also make it easier for them to participate in the
  <b>
   standard-setting process
  </b>
  , win
  <b>
   public procurement contracts
  </b>
  and
turn
  <b>
   environmental challenges into business opportunities
  </b>
  .
 </p>
 <p>
  Finally, the SBA seeks new ways to
  <b>
   stimulate interest in
entrepreneurship
  </b>
  and cultivate a
  <b>
   more entrepreneurial mindset, especially
among young people
  </b>
  . Young people, who want to start up a business, can now
gain experience by spending time in an SME abroad via the just launched
“Erasmus for young entrepreneurs” programme. This will help upgrade
their skills and contribute to the networking among SMEs in Europe. Similar
mobility programmes are also underway for apprentices.
 </p>
 <p>
  The SBA is fully embedded in the Growth and Jobs strategy. Member States are
invited to take advantage of the update of the Lisbon cycle 2008 to reflect the
SBA in their National Reform Programmes.
 </p>
 <p>
  <b>
   Background
  </b>
 </p>
 <p>
  Although 99% of companies in the EU are SMEs (companies with a maximum of 250
employees and a maximal turnover of € 50 million), most legislation and
administrative procedures don’t distinguish on the basis of company size.
As a result, 23 million SMEs often have the same administrative requirements as
Europe’s 41,000 large companies. During past years SMEs have created 80 %
of the new jobs in the EU.
 </p>
 <p>
  More information
 </p>
 <p>
  <a href="http://ec.europa.eu/enterprise/entrepreneurship/sba_en.htm" title="http://ec.europa.eu/enterprise/entrepreneurship/sba_en.htm">
   http://ec.europa.eu/enterprise/entrepreneurship/sba_en.htm
  </a>
 </p>
 <p>
  <b>
   European Investment Bank consultation report:
  </b>
 </p>
 <p>
  <a href="http://www.eib.org/attachments/strategies/sme-consultation-2007-2008-en.pdf" title="http://www.eib.org/attachments/strategies/sme-consultation-2007-2008-en.pdf">
   http://www.eib.org/attachments/strategies/sme-consultation-2007-2008-en.pdf
  </a>
 </p>
</document>
