<document celex="IP-08-1017" lang="en">
 <p align="right">
  <b>
   IP/08/1017
  </b>
 </p>
 <p align="right">
  Brussels, 26 June 2008
 </p>
 <h1>
  <a name="Heading4">
  </a>
  <b>
   Information from the Public Sector now
easier to re-use in all Member States. Easy enough? asks Commission in a new
public consultation
  </b>
 </h1>
 <h2>
  <a name="Heading7">
  </a>
  <b>
   <i>
    Public bodies produce, collect and share vast
amounts of information, such as meteorological, traffic and financial data,
digital maps or tourist information. This valuable Public Sector Information can
be the basis of new added value services, but it is often difficult for
businesses and individuals to re-use it. The EU's Public Sector Information
Directive of 2003 enhances the re-use of such information across the EU.
Transposition of the Directive has now been completed in all 27 EU Member
States, as the European Commission has now closed an infringement case against
Belgium for non-transposition of the Directive. The Commission is currently
evaluating the corresponding national laws in preparation of a review of the
Public Sector Information Directive which is due by the end of 2008. It has
launched a public consultation towards this aim, which is open until 31 July
2008.
   </i>
  </b>
 </h2>
 <p>
  "When using your car navigation system, you are enjoying the services built
on public sector information. This is only one example out of thousands. Public
sector information is a very important resource for Europe's digital industry,"
said Viviane Reding, EU Commissioner for Information Society and Media. "Now
that the legislation is in place in all Member States, we need to ensure that it
is working in practice."
 </p>
 <p>
  Public sector information is an extraordinary resource for the EU's digital
content industry. According to a survey made in 2006, the overall market size
for public sector information in the EU is estimated at â&sbquo;Ź 27 billion. The
EU's Public Sector Information Directive aims to overcome market barriers such
as unfair competitive advantage for those public organisations that themselves
commercialise the information they generate over private companies through for
example cumbersome licensing procedures and high charges. Exclusive arrangements
awarded by public organisations to one company for exploiting public sector
information are to be terminated by end of 2008, thus unlocking important
information resources for many re-users. The Directive also obliges Member
States to overcome lack of information on availability of public sector
information and to clarify the conditions for its re-use. These measures are
necessary to create a single market for information and provide European
companies with a single set of rules
  <a href="">
   .
  </a>
 </p>
 <p>
  All 27 EU Member States have now transposed the Directive in their national
laws. Belgium announced that it had done so on 8 May 2008, following the
judgement of the European Court of Justice of 13 December 2007 (C-2006/528).
 </p>
 <p>
  The European Commission has recently published an
  <a href="http://ec.europa.eu/information_society/policy/psi/docs/pdfs/online_consultation/review.pdf">
   online
public consultation
  </a>
  to gather information from stakeholders on the
implementation, impact and scope of the Public Sector Information Directive. The
consultation is
  <b>
   open until 31 July 2008
  </b>
  and its results will feed into
the review of the Directive.
 </p>
 <p>
  <b>
   Background:
  </b>
 </p>
 <p>
  The Public Sector Information Directive was adopted by the European
Parliament and the Council of Ministers in November 2003. It is aimed to offer
means for public sector bodies to enhance the re-use of their information
resources by setting up rules to deal with requests for re-use or availability
of documents. Member States had 18 months (until 1 July 2005) to transpose the
Directive into their national laws.Â The European
  <a href="http://ec.europa.eu/information_society/policy/psi/actions_eu/policy_actions/monitoring/index_en.htm">
   Commission
is monitoring
  </a>
  the implementation of the Directive in the Member Sates. The
closure of the Belgian case (started by the Commission on 12 October 2005 and
submitted to the European Court of Justice on 12 December 2006 (
  <a href="http://europa.eu/rapid/pressReleasesAction.do?reference=IP/06/1891&amp;format=HTML&amp;aged=0&amp;language=EN&amp;guiLanguage=en">
   IP/06/1891
  </a>
  )
paves the way for a more efficient application of these rules across the EU.
 </p>
 <p>
  <b>
   The Commission's public consultation document on the review of the Public
Sector Information Directive can be found on:
  </b>
 </p>
 <p>
  <a href="http://ec.europa.eu/information_society/policy/psi/index_en.htm">
   http://ec.europa.eu/information_society/policy/psi/index_en.htm
  </a>
 </p>
 <p>
  <b>
   Contributions to the public consultation can be sent to:
  </b>
 </p>
 <p>
  <a href="mailto:infso-psihelp@ec.europa.eu">
   infso-psihelp@ec.europa.eu
  </a>
 </p>
</document>
